Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
Colonial National Historical Park, National Park Service
Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
For additional information on these holdings, contact the holding institution. Contact information is available from the VIVA Special Collections web page: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/viva/links.html
Administrative Information
Access restrictions
Contact holding institution
Introduction
The scope of a comprehensive bibliography on Jamestown must necessarily be broad, spanning the whole range of the site's history from 1607 to 2007, from English exploration and colonization to the era of American hegemony and nostalgia, from the matchlock to ground-penetrating radar, from iron-helmeted mercenaries seeking gold and glory for King and Church to the denim-clad troops of Historical Archaeology and High Academe digging carefully into earth and archive for nuggets of the past, from the enigmatic daughter of a tribal leader to a larger-than-life heroine of Hollywood hype, from the early proselytizers of adventure and fortune to historians describing in turn the mythical and the factual, from the coffee klatch of gentlewomen hoping to preserve their visions of ancestral valor to the planners and promoters of past and future celebrations of Jamestown's "firsts."
The variety of formats represented among the entries of such a bibliography must also be extensive, covering the range of technologies used to record data and dreams throughout the period. There are manuscripts and archives; books and pamphlets; periodical articles, research reports, and lectures; songs, poems, plays, and novels; maps, charts, paintings, sound recordings, and films; and, yes, even computer programs.
This document has all of the above and more, but it does not have everything. From the beginning it has been understood that the bibliography would be not only a lengthy listing of resources, but also an exercise in compiling such a tool using computer software, thereby creating a database which could easily be supplemented in the future. The resources dedicated to the bibliography were never sufficient to generate an exhaustive compilation covering the four centuries of Jamestown's recorded history. The database, however, can be augmented as new materials are produced and as earlier documents are discovered and cataloged.
The bibliography has been created under a Cooperative Agreement between the National Park Service and the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation. The entire project is known as the Jamestown Archaeological Assessment. Its goal has been to undertake archaeological, historical, and bibliographic studies that can be used by the Park Service in evaluating and managing the cultural resources on Jamestown Island.
Much of the bibliographic work of the assessment project was undertaken by the project's historian, who visited depositories and record offices, scanned newspapers and periodicals, identified relevant maps and other charts, and created databases citing references to Jamestown in all of these sources. The databases are invaluable resources which, as of the publication of this report, exist outside the formal bibliography.
The bibliography itself was generated principally by two methods-searching online bibliographic databases and perusing published works and their reference lists. Initially, a large number of foreign and domestic depositories were queried in search of documents that might contain clues to Jamestown's past. This strategy, however, rarely produced sufficient information to comprise an entry in the bibliography, though it did provide the project historian with a few intriguing leads. (Most depositories do not have finding aids at a level of detail that would allow a busy staff person to locate relevant citations without extensive research. Such a task would require on-site visits by experienced historians possessing adequate language and research skills. The responses to our polling of the depositories indicate that this is an area of inquiry that is worthy of pursuit. Archives in Spain and the Netherlands seem to offer especially good prospects for useful results.)
The online databases searched were the OCLC Online Computer Library Center, the RLIN Bibliographic Files of Research Libraries Group, and the DIALOG service of Knight-Ridder Information, Inc. Records relating to Jamestown, Virginia, were downloaded from these databases and transferred by way of Biblio-Link into ProCite databases. Biblio-Link and ProCite are computer programs published by Research Information Systems. ProCite is the bibliographic management software that was designated by the National Park Service for use in creating the assessment project's bibliography.
Depositories known to be holding the original or a copy of the map are noted in each entry. Most maps are available at the John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library of the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation. The bibliographer examined the maps at the Rockefeller Library and used the title and imprint information as it appears on each chart, with some punctuation changes to enhance logic and clarity.
Entries on audiovisual materials in sections 14 through 18 often include information on accompanying literature, such as a teacher's guide. Pictorial Works, in Section 19, include paintings, posters, prints, and stereographs.
Section 21 has entries describing conference papers, periodical articles, and project reports generated by assessment project staff during the five years of the Cooperative Agreement.
References in the indexes are to entry numbers, not page numbers. Numerous index listings have been added in order to cite authors and titles which are noted in the bibliography but which do not have separate entries of their own.
After the principal bibliography was compiled, The National Park Service reviewed and noted about thirty additional entries that they would like to have included. Rather than reformat the text and indexes, these were added to the end of the ProCite database and then individually inserted in the printed document. For this reason, occasionally entry numbers may appear "out of order" (for example, 1217 may be between 470 and 471). To facilitate ease of use, in this case both the entry number and page number are included in the index (e.g., 1217 (PAGE 172)).
The Author Index includes individual authors, corporate authors, illustrators, editors, compilers, cartographers, surveyors, engravers, composers, producers, directors, and any other contributors that might be noted in entries.
The subject headings used in the Subject Index, and also in the Keywords fields of the ProCite database, are based on Library of Congress Subject Headings, 18th ed. (Washington: 1995), with some adaptations. Since this bibliography is about a particular place, most geographic subdivisions would be redundant. The main heading "Jamestown (Va.)" is used, however, with such general subdivisions as "Description and travel" and "History" and with form subdivisions such as "Guidebooks," "Juvenile literature," and "Pictorial works."
Listings in the Index to Place Names on Maps appear as they are spelled on the maps. References to Jamestown, for example, might be found under lames T., Iamestown, James To., James Town, and several other forms. The index includes sites on or near Jamestown Island. References to Williamsburg (established in 1699) are given only for eighteenth-century maps.
The ProCite database of bibliographic records has additional information that does not appear in this printed bibliography. A few items have not been included if they could not be examined directly and if their records are too incomplete to be useful. Some records in the ProCite database contain references to book reviews or to microform versions of the work. If the form of the author's name on a work differs from uniform entry, the variant is cited in a note. For obscure items entered from OCLC records, the name of the cataloging library is given as a suggestion of availability. The ProCite database will be in the possession of the National Park Service at the end of the assessment project. Its subsequent availability is yet to be determined.
The Jamestown Archaeological Assessment's first bibliographer was Susan Shames, Decorative Arts Librarian at the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation. In the early months of the project, she developed a plan for the bibliography, installed ProCite and entered the first records, sent query letters to more than 130 foreign and domestic archives, and generously bestowed upon her successor the benefits of her hard work and knowledge.
Among those at the outset who provided counsel and suggested a course of action were John Haskell (Swem Library, College of William and Mary), Karen Ordahl Kupperman (University of Connecticut), Helen Wallis (Map Division, British Library), David and Alison Quinn (Liverpool), David Ransome (Rhode Island School of Design), Lorena Walsh (Colonial Williamsburg Foundation), and Martha McCartney. As the project's historian, however, Ms. McCartney has been a valued colleague for the duration. She identified most of the maps listed in Section 13, and her tireless sleuthing has produced files of data from countless sources detailing the story of Jamestown.
The central role of computers in the assembling of this bibliography produced a heavy reliance on technical support. Beth Nagle (Information Technology, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation) gave sound advice on hardware and later installed software for the project. Bettina Manzo (Swem Library, College of William and Mary), Chuck Ralkind (National Park Service-Yorktown), and librarians Effie Nicosia, Don Dowdey and Garland Gouger (NASA-Langley) shared their experiences as ProCite users. Much helpful assistance was sought and obtained from customer service personnel at Personal Bibliographic Software, SOLINET, OCLC, RLIN, and Research Information Systems, most notably Karen Jordan (PBS) and Diane Brown (SOLINET).
Seventy-five percent of the depositories that were queried at the beginning of the project graciously responded. As leads developed or questions arose regarding a specific collection or document, other inquiries were dispatched. Helpful responses came from W. J. Hitchens at the University of Sheffield; Donald Gibson at the Kent County (England) Archives; Mary Sampson at the Royal Society in London; Mrs. P. Thomson at the William Salt Library, Stafford, England; R. M. Haubourdin at the Algemeen Rijksarchief in The Hague; Pilar Lazaro de la Escosura at the Archivo General de Indias in Seville; William R. Erwin, Jr., at Duke University; Eva M. Chandler, Margaret D. Hrabe, and Robin D. Wear at the University of Virginia's Alderman Library; E. Lee Shepard at the Virginia Historical Society; Mary Dessypris and John Kneebone at the Library of Virginia; Gretchen Schneider and Ann Berry at the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities; Margaret Cook at Swem Library, College of William and Mary; Eric G. Ackermann at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; and staff at Macalaster College's DeWitt Wallace Library and at the Montgomery County (Ohio) Records Center and Archives.
Assessment project team members submitted copies of reports, articles, and conference papers for inclusion in the bibliography. Cary Carson, senior principal investigator, provided guidance within an atmosphere conducive to independent work. Greg Brown has been very helpful with the preparation of the final report. Administrative and clerical support was ably supplied by Wendy Sumerlin and Lynn Fletcher. National Park Service staff, including Jane Sundberg, Jim Haskett, David Riggs, and Diane Stallings, gave advice, information, and encouragement.
The John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library and its predecessor, the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library, have provided "headquarters" for the bibliography project, as well as the bibliographer's other job. The cooperation and support of the library staff have been crucial to the accomplishment of this work. Numerous interlibrary loans were arranged by Lois Danuser. Suggestions from Mary Haskell and Julie Conlee helped facilitate access to online services. John Ingram, Gail Greve, and George Yetter in the Special Collections Department gathered maps, acquired microfilm, and located obscure uncataloged items in the vault. A willing assist and a smile were always available from Inge Flester.
The bibliographer's participation in this project would have been impossible without the encouragement and support of Susan Berg and Liz Ackert, Director and Public Services Librarian respectively at the Rockefeller Library. Among their many contributions were a boost at the start, clarification of goals, ongoing advice, work space, flexible scheduling, technical support, and practical solutions to unforeseen problems.
Foreword
The ten-volume Jamestown Archaeological Assessment (JAA) represents the culmination of six decades of archaeology conducted by the National Park Service on one of the most significant sites in North America. In the 1930s, J. C. Harrington, the father of historical archaeology, conducted the first surveys of New Towne that identified the foundations of major buildings from the seventeenth-century capital city. In the 1950s, John L. Cotter developed a grid system for New Towne that resulted in the development of a historical base map, which proved to be invaluable for the JAA team. Then in the late 1980s, James N. Haskett, Assistant Superintendent, identified the need to survey the entire portion of Jamestown Island owned by the National Park Service. The objectives of this survey were to test new methods of locating archaeological sites, evaluate their effectiveness, and ensure a comprehensive and integrated approach. The Assessment included the relationship of the natural environment to the historical events, historical documentation of land ownership and those who lived on Jamestown Island, an analysis of artifacts and skeletal material previously uncovered, and using the latest technology, i.e., Geographical Information Systems, to document the discoveries. As we approach the 400th anniversary of Jamestown in 2007, this assessment will serve as a guiding light for the preservation and interpretation of America's birthplace well into the next century.
I wish to thank for their dedicated service and enthusiasm: James Haskett, Dr. David G. Orr, Jane Sundberg, David Riggs, Diane Stallings, Chuck Rafkind, Karen G. Rehm, and other members of the park staff. The research teams of the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, as directed by Dr. Cary Carson and Dr. Marley Brown, III, and The College of William and Mary, under the direction of Dennis Blanton, who prepared the studies, are to be commended for their scholarly and thorough approach. Last but not least, I acknowledge the support of Kate Stevenson, Associate Director, Cultural Resource Stewardship and Partnerships, National Park Service, and the Jamestown Rediscovery project team under the direction of Dr. William Kelso of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities in their roles as partners in preserving and studying Jamestown. The printing of this study is funded in part by the Valley Forge Center for Cultural Resources.
Alec Gould, Superintendent, Colonial National Historical Park
Contents List
- Archives/Manuscripts
  - Ambler Family Papers 1772-1852., 1; 159 items.
    Family members represented include John Ambler (1762-1830), lawyer and planter of Jamestown, James City County, Richmond, and Williamsburg, and lieutenant colonel in the Virginia militia; and his son Phillip St. George Ambler (1806-1877). Materials include John Ambler's correspondence (1792-1832, 81 items) concerning the Virginia militia, slaves, the James River Company, and the War of 1812; accounts (1797-1836, 28 items); deeds for land and slaves; and Virginia militia muster rolls and other materials (1797-1814, 19 items). Also included are letters (1830-1852, 10 items) written to Phillip St. George Ambler and scattered correspondence and accounts of other Ambler family members. Unpublished description available.
  - Ambler, John. Papers 1770-1860, 2
    Includes an 1800 overseer's agreement relating to John Ambler's "James Town" plantation.
  - Ambler, John Jaquelin. The History of the Ambler Family in Virginia, 1826., 3; 147 pp.
    Concerned with the descendants of Richard Ambler of "Little York" and Elizabeth Jaquelin of Jamestown, who were married in 1729. John Jaquelin Ambler, the eldest son of John and Catherine Norton Ambler, was born in Williamsburg in 1801. Includes an index of names.
  - Ambler Papers 1638-1809., 4; 135 items.
    Land grants, deeds, surveys, bonds, indentures, and other land papers from the vicinity of Jamestown and the Fairfax Proprietary estates of the Northern Neck. Names represented include Richard Ambler and family, Sir Edmund Andros, Nathaniel Bacon, Sir William Berkeley, the Beverley family, Lord Howard of Effingham, Sir William Gooch, Henry Hartwell, Francis Nicholson, and Alexander Spotswood.
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities. Papers 1889-1947., 5; 62 items.
    The collection contains items relating to the operation of the Association's historic site at Jamestown, including three volumes of accounts (1907-1936), mostly kept by Mary Washington Ball (Minor) Lightfoot, chair of the Jamestown Committee, and a few loose accounts (1936-1947). Also, an 1892 membership list; a record of correspondence (1889-1893) kept by Lucy Parke (Chamberlayne) Bagby; and letters (1889-1904) to an early president, Isobel Lamont (Stewart) Bryan. Unpublished description available.
  - ---. [Proposed Agreement between the A.P.V.A. and the National Park Service 1940., 6; 3 pieces.
    Mimeographed. Includes a copy of the agreement, a statement by an attorney for the Association, and a cover letter.
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Colonial Capitol Branch, Williamsburg, Va. Records 1898-1980., 7; 1802 items.
    Includes correspondence, financial and legal documents, minutes and photographs. The long run of minutes, 1900-1976, document the development and work of this preservation group, which took an interest in the historical sites of Jamestown and Williamsburg. Also included are photographs of Jamestown Island (1900-1910). Inventory available in library.
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Washington Branch. Records 1931-1957., 8; 2 linear ft.
    Most materials in this collection date from 1946 to 1955, when Emily Withers was Director. Included are minutes of meetings, annual reports, information about special events, clippings, photographs, and pamphlets concerning specific tours and speakers. Topics include APVA activities and historic properties, such as Jamestown. Guide available.
  - Bagby, Ellen M. Papers 1939 October 5., 10 p.
    The papers consist of reports submitted to APVA concerning the remodeling of the Museum and Relic House, possible construction of a new building, and a possible agreement of cooperation between the National Park Service and APVA
  - Bagby Family Papers 1824-1960., 9; 53,178 items.
    The correspondence of Lucy Parke (Chamberlayne) Bagby (1842-1927) includes items relating to the APVA. The papers of Parke's daughter Ellen Matthews Bagby (1879-1960) include correspondence concerning the operation of APVA properties at Jamestown in the mid-twentieth century.
  - Barbour, Philip L. Papers 1935-1980., 10; 2,247 items.
    The papers of Philip Lemont Barbour (1898-1980) include research notes for his historical writings on the settlement of North America. Most articles, clippings and notes concern people associated with Captain John Smith. Correspondents include Lawrence W. Towner, 1960-1967, and representatives of the National Gallery of Art and the Smithsonian Institution, 1964-1969. There is also some printed material (mostly copies) dating back to 1603. Inventory available in library.
  - Barraud, Philip. Letters to St. George Tucker. 1791-1827, 11
    Philip Barraud (1757-1830) was a physician who lived in Williamsburg from 1782 to 1799, when he moved back to Norfolk to be head of the Marine Hospital. Subjects of letters include a trip to Jamestown, yellow fever epidemics in 1800 and 1821, and the War of 1812. Chronological card inventory available. Originals are in the Tucker-Coleman Collection, Swem Library, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg.
  - Bath Papers 1607-1778., 12
    Reference: Thomas J. Wertenbaker, Bacon's Rebellion, 1676, pp. 59-60: "The opening to investigators of the Marquess of Bath Papers by the British Manuscripts Project has thrown new light on Bacon's Rebellion. There are several letters from Bacon to Berkeley and several from Berkeley to Bacon. They show that Berkeley went to England during the Civil War to fight for the King, that Bacon was related to Lady Berkeley, that Lady Berkeley was in England during most of the rebellion, and that she corresponded with Philip Ludwell. The Bath Papers add to the already abundant evidence that Bacon fought partly to end misgovernment in Virginia. The evidence comes not only from Bacon's supporters but from Berkeley himself, Ludwell, and others." "Berkeley's letters explain why he did not hang Bacon when he had him in his power, why he dissolved the Long Assembly and called for a new election based on a widened franchise, why he evacuated the almost impregnable post of Jamestown. There are several revealing letters by Philip Ludwell."
  - Bemiss, Samuel Merrifield. Papers 1936-1964., ca.1,000 items.
    Prominent businessman and civic leader, of Richmond, Va., who served as vice-president of the U.S. Jamestown-Williamsburg-Yorktown Celebration Commission and as a board member of the Jamestown Foundation. Correspondents discussing the Jamestown Festival of 1957 include Francis Lewis Berkeley, Frank Learoyd Boyden, Thomas Bahnson Stanley, Earl Gregg Swem, and Conrad Louis Wirth.
  - Blair, James. Papers ca. 1701-1747., 13; 1 box.
    James Blair (d. 1743) was appointed commissary of the Bishop of London and minister of Jamestown Church in 1689 and rector of Bruton Parish Church in 1710. He was instrumental in founding the College of William and Mary and served as its first president. Papers include biographical material, correspondence, sermons, and a copy of Blair's commission as commissary of the Bishop of London in Virginia. Inventory available in library.
  - Breeden, Edward Lebbaius. Papers 1932-1972., 14; 26,000 items (32 ft.)
    Political papers from Breeden's career in the Virginia House of Delegates and the State Senate constitute the bulk of the material. Included are papers relating to Breeden's work on the Jamestown Festival Commission.
  - Burrell, Mary Ann Mary Terretta. Papers 1839-1959., 247 items.
    Burrell emigrated from Siberia to Chesterfield County, Va., as a child. As an adult she was a school teacher and journalist until her marriage. Among her papers are manuscripts of unpublished children's books set in historic Virginia locations. Titles include "Chanco," "The Maid of Jamestown," and "Rural Retreat."
  - Burwell, Charles S. Letter 1861 June 2., 4 p.
    Burwell was stationed on Jamestown Island with the 14th Virginia Infantry. His letter to his brother describes the quality of rations the layout of the island, its fortifications, and the number of men stationed there.
  - Business Men's Association of the City of Williamsburg, Jamestown Tercentennial Committee. Circular 1901., [4] p., printed.